A Guide to the Virginius Dabney Papers 1944-1971
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Virginius Dabney Papers, 1944-1971
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7690-m
This collection contains 34 boxes of material.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This holding was acquired as a gift.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Virginius Dabney contain extensive correspondence carried on by Dabney as editor of the Richmond Times-Dispatch, in his personal life, and as a Pulitzer Prize- winning author. Other materials deal with his books such as Below the Potomac, The Dry Messiah, and Liberalism in the South, and much useful material collected as research material for these books is present. There is extensive material on the American Society of Newspaper Editors which Dabney served in various capacities including president. A great deal of useful material on race relations, African Americans, the N.A.A.C.P., etc., is present. Recent political history of Virginia is strongly represented in Dabney's correspondence as editor of Virginia's leading newspaper, and in his personal correspondence with figures such as Senator A. Willis Robinson, Francis Pickens Miller, and Senator Carter Glass.
Contents List
- A 1958-1961 (Box 1)
- Aiken, Newton 1950-1968 (Box 1)
- Almond, J. Lindsay July 17, 1962 (Box 1)
- American Magazine, "School Crisis in Dixie" 1955-1958 (Box 1)
- American Society of Newspaper Editors 1959 (Box 1)
- American Society of Newspaper Editors 1960 (Box 1)
- American Society of Newspaper Editors 1962 (Box 1)
- American Society of Newspaper Editors 1963 (Box 1)
- "Appomatox," Reader's Digest, Saturday Review of Literature1954-1968 (Box 2)
- Auburn football 1957-1958 (Box 1)
- Ba-Bh 1956-1961 (Box 1)
- Battle, William C. May 28, 1962 (Box 1)
- Begien, R.N., Jr. 1964 (Box 1)
- Francis L. Berkeley 1948-1963 (Box 1)
- Bi-Bq 1958-1961 (Box 1)
- Book review requests 1954 (Box 3)
- Boyle, Sarah Patton 1952-1962 (Box 3)
- Br-Bt 1955-1961 (Box 3)
- Brown, D. Malcolm 1962 (Box 3)
- Bryan, Wright 1963-1965 (Box 3)
- Bu-Bz 1959-1961 (Box 3)
- Byrd, Harry Flood, Sr. 1941-1954 (Box 3)
- Byrd, Harry Flood, Sr. 1955-1965 (Box 3)
- Ca-Cg 1957-1961 (Box 4)
- Cartoon requests, Siebel 1950-1956 (Box 4)
- Ch-Cn 1954-1961 (Box 4)
- Cincinnati, Society of 1965, 1968 (Box 4)
- Co-Cq 1957-1962 (Box 4)
- Cochran, George M. 1966-1967 (Box 4)
- Conte, Paul 1968 (Box 4)
- Country Club of Virginia 1953-1963 (Box 5)
- Country Club of Virginia 1953-1963 (Box 5)
- Country Club of Virginia 1953-1963 (Box 5)
- Cousins, Norman 1944-1964 (Box 5)
- Cr-Cz 1959-1960 (Box 5)
- Crawford, Bruce 1954-1967 (Box 5)
- Da-Dn 1959-1962 (Box 6)
- Da-Dn 1959-1962 (Box 6)
- Da-Dn 1959-1962 (Box 6)
- Dabneys of Virginia 1952-1960 (Box 6)
- Do-Dz 1957-1962 (Box 6)
- Durham, M.W. 1955-1965 (Box 6)
- E 1955-1960 (Box 7)
- Fa-Fn 1958-1961 (Box 7)
- Faulkner, Mrs. Charles J. 1964-1968 (Box 7)
- Fitzpatrick, William H. 1958-1962 (Box 7)
- Fleming, Charles C. 1946-1963 (Box 7)
- Fo-Fz 1959-1965 (Box 7)
- Forum Club 1953-1969 (Box 7)
- Ga-Gk 1958-1962 (Box 8)
- Gaines, Francis P. 1947-1962 (Box 8)
- Garnett, W.E. 1947-1948 (Box 8)
- Gary, J. Vaughan 1960-1964 (Box 8)
- Germany 1960-1963 (Box 8)
- Gibson, George D. 1959-1968 (Box 8)
- Gl-Gz 1953-1961 (Box 8)
- Graves, John Temple II 1948-1961 (Box 8)
- Haa-Hal 1957-1961 (Box 9)
- Hagan, J. Addison 1962-1968 (Box 9)
- Ham-Hd 1958-1960 (Box 9)
- Ham-Hd 1958-1960 (Box 9)
- Harper's article 1961-1963 (Box 9)
- He-Hn 1958-1961 (Box 9)
- Historic St. Luke's Restoration 1953-1955 (Box 9)
- Ho-Ht 1950-1962 (Box 10)
- Holbert, Jesse (Lt.) ca. 1944-1950 (Box 10)
- Holiday Magazine 1947-1963 (Box 10)
- Howard, A.E. (Dick) 1964-1968 (Box 10)
- Hu-Hz 1959-1961 (Box 10)
- I 1952-1961 (Box 10)
- Institute of Early American History and Culture 1948-1957 (Box 10)
- J 1957-1961 (Box 10)
- (Box 10)
- Jamestown article 1954-1959 (Box 11)
- Jamestown article 1954-1959 (Box 11)
- Joint Civilian Orientation Conference 1960-1964 (Box 11)
- Ka-Kk 1954-1961 (Box 11)
- Kane, Harnett T. 1948-1965 (Box 12)
- Kl-Kz 1955-1961 (Box 12)
- La-Ld 1955-1962 (Box 12)
- Le-Ln 1955-1961 (Box 12)
- Life magazine article--Segregation 1958 (Box 13)
- Life magazine article--Segregation 1958 (Box 13)
- Life magazine article--Segregation 1958 (Box 13)
- Life magazine article--Segregation 1958 (Box 13)
- Life magazine 1956 (Box 13)
- Lo-Lz 1955-1961 (Box 13)
- Ma-Mb 1956-1963 (Box 14)
- Marshall, Chief Justice John (article) 1955-1957 (Box 14)
- Marshall, Collier 1943-1966 (Box 14)
- May Reading File May, 1958 (Box 14)
- Mc-Md 1958-1963 (Box 14)
- McClary, Rev. Webster 1955 (Box 14)
- Me-Mn 1949-1961 (Box 14)
- Miller, Col. Francis Pickens 1949-1950 (Box 14)
- Mo-Mz 1958-1963 (Box 15)
- Mo-Mz 1958-1963 (Box 15)
- Mytton-Thornycroft, Nigel (Rhodesia) 1966 (Box 15)
- "N" 1958-1961 (Box 15)
- National Association of Secondary School Principals Speech 1957-1961 (Box 16)
- National Association of Secondary School Principals Speech 1957-1961 (Box 16)
- National Conference of Christians and Jews 1947-1966 (Box 17)
- National Conference of Christians and Jews 1947-1966 (Box 17)
- National Conference of Christians and Jews 1947-1966 (Box 17)
- National Conference of Christians and Jews 1947-1966 (Box 17)
- National Municipal League 1953 (Box 18)
- Newcomen Society 1964-1965 (Box 18)
- New York University scholarships 1951-1956 (Box 18)
- Nixon, Richard M. 1961-1968 (Box 18)
- Nutter, G. Warren 1957-1965 (Box 18)
- O 1959-1962 (Box 18)
- Pa-Ph 1959-1966 (Box 18)
- Patterson, John M. 1955-1963 (Box 18)
- Pegler, Westbrook 1954-1961 (Box 18)
- Dabney, Virginius (Denmark, Finland, Norway, Sweden) 1966-1967 (Box 19)
- Dabney, Virginius (France) 1966 (Box 19)
- Personal 1954-1958 (Box 19)
- Personal 1948-1961 (Box 19)
- Personal 1955-1961 (Box 19)
- Personal 1950-1961 (Box 19)
- Personal 1961-1969 (Box 19)
- Phi Beta Kappa, Richmond Chapter 1953-1954 (Box 20)
- Pi-Pz 1958-1961 (Box 20)
- Pomfret, John E. 1944-1960 (Box 20)
- Prohibition 1953-1954 (Box 20)
- Putnam, Carleton 1959 (Box 20)
- Q 1955-1961 (Box 20)
- Ra-Rn 1958-1961 (Box 20)
- Reader's Digest 1954-1962 (Box 21)
- Retirement Letters 1968-1969 (Box 21)
- Retirement Letters 1968-1969 (Box 21)
- Retirement Letters 1968-1969 (Box 21)
- Rhodes Scholarship Committee 1952-1959 (Box 21)
- Richmond Public Forum 1948-1959 (Box 22)
- Richmond Public Library 1960-1963 (Box 22)
- Richmond Public Library 1959-1960 (Box 22)
- Richmond Public Library 1947-1956 (Box 22)
- Richmond Public Library 1955-1959 (Box 22)
- Richmond Public Library 1955-1959 (Box 22)
- Richmond Symphony 1959-1962 (Box 23)
- Richmond Symphony 1964-1968 (Box 23)
- Ro-Rz 1956-1961 (Box 23)
- Robert, Joseph C. 1960-1966 (Box 23)
- Robertson, A. Willis 1967-1968 (Box 23)
- Robertson, Walter S. (Box 23)
- Roderick, Mrs. Mary Louise 1962-1966 (Box 23)
- Rouse, Parke, Jr. 1951-1967 (Box 23)
- Rubin, Louis D., Sr. 1959-1960 (Box 23)
- Sa-Sb 1953-1954 (Box 24)
- Satterfield, David E. III 1967-1968 (Box 24)
- Saturday Evening Post, suggested articles 1953-1963 (Box 24)
- Saturday Evening Post, Thanksgiving article 1958-1964 (Box 24)
- Saunders, Richard T. 1952-1968 (Box 24)
- Saunders, Robert C. 1952-1957 (Box 24)
- Saunier, Paul 1962-1965 (Box 24)
- Sc-Sd 1959-1961 (Box 24)
- Se-Sj 1957-1961 (Box 24)
- Segregation 1954-1955, 1986 (Box 25)
- Seibel, Fred O. 1968-1970 (Box 25)
- Shannon, Edgar F., (President, UVA) 1966-1968 (Box 25)
- Sk-Ss 1958-1961 (Box 25)
- South Africa 1965 (Box 25)
- Southern Regional Council, Inc. 1954-1958 (Box 25)
- Southern Regional Council, Inc. 1954-1958 (Box 25)
- Spain; Portugal 1965-1966 (Box 25)
- Speaking Engagements 1957-1962 (Box 26)
- Speaking Engagements 1957-1962 (Box 26)
- Speaking Engagements 1966-1969 (Box 26)
- Speaking Engagements 1966-1969 (Box 26)
- St-Sz 1959-1961 (Box 26)
- Stegall, Mrs. N.G. 1958-1964 (Box 27)
- Strauss, Lewis L. 1953-1968 (Box 27)
- Strode, Hudson 1950-1967 (Box 27)
- Strode, Hudson 1950-1967 (Box 27)
- Swem, Earl G. 1954-1965 (Box 27)
- T 1957-1961 (Box 27)
- T 1957-1961 (Box 27)
- Taylor, Henry J. 1949-1968 (Box 28)
- Taylor, Henry P. 1962-1966 (Box 28)
- Templeton, Kenneth S. 1960-1967 (Box 28)
- Thalheimer, Morton G. 1962-1967 (Box 28)
- This Week Magazine 1953-1960 (Box 28)
- Tucker, Dr. Robert H. 1963-1967 (Box 28)
- U-V 1958-1961 (Box 28)
- Virginia Academy of Science--Long Range Planning Committee 1944-1954 (Box 28)
- Virginia Commonwealth University--Congratulations, Correspondence 1968 (Box 28)
- Virginia Council of Churches 1949-1954 (Box 28)
- Virginia Historical Society 1950-1962 (Box 29)
- Virginia Historical Society 1950-1962 (Box 29)
- Virginia Historical Society 1950-1962 (Box 29)
- Virginia Historical Society 1950-1962 (Box 29)
- Virginia Historical Society 1950-1962 (Box 29)
- Virginia Historical Society 1950-1962 (Box 29)
- Voice of the People--Permission to use letter 1954-1957 (Box 30)
- Voice of the People--Rejects 1960-1962 (Box 30)
- Voice of the People--Rejects 1960-1962 (Box 30)
- Wa-Wd 1955-1961 (Box 30)
- Wa-Wd 1955-1961 (Box 30)
- Waring, Thomas R. 1965-1967 (Box 31)
- We-Wh 1954-1961 (Box 31)
- We-Wh 1954-1961 (Box 31)
- Wellford, Dabney 1965-1967 (Box 31)
- Wertenbaker, Dr. Thomas J. 1950-1966 (Box 31)
- White, William S. 1967 (Box 31)
- Wi-Wz 1954-1961 (Box 31)
- Wi-Wz 1954-1961 (Box 31)
- Wilkinson, J. Harvie 1953-1968 (Box 31)
- Wilkinson, J. Harvie, Jr. 1967-1968 (Box 31)
- Willett, Henry I. 1952-1963 (Box 31)
- Williams, John Bell 1962-1965 (Box 32)
- Williams, Langbourne 1963-1965 (Box 32)
- Williams, Martin 1965-1966 (Box 32)
- Williams, Murat W. 1966 (Box 32)
- Williams, Robert R., Ex-Secretary, Virginia Education Association 1948-1968 (Box 32)
- Wilkie, Philip H. 1954-1964 (Box 32)
- Wise, Henry A. 1963-1967 (Box 32)
- Wolfe, Henry C. 1953-1965 (Box 32)
- Wood, Charles P. 1952-1968 (Box 32)
- Woodard, Prince B. 1965-1966 (Box 32)
- Woodrow Wilson Centennial 1955-1958 (Box 32)
- Woodrow Wilson Centennial 1955-1958 (Box 32)
- Woodward, C. Vann 1958-1967 (Box 33)
- Woodward, Fletcher D. 1948-1968 (Box 33)
- Woodward, Harry 1962-1964 (Box 33)
- Wranek, William H., Jr. 1944-1960 (Box 33)
- Wranek, William H. Jr. 1944-1960 (Box 33)
- Wright, David McCord 1949-1957 (Box 33)
- Wright, Louis B. -- Folger Library 1950-1958 (Box 33)
- Wyllie, John Cook 1948-1967 (Box 33)
- Wyllie, John Cook, Librarian, Alderman Library, U.Va--Dabney Papers 1959-1968 (Box 33)
- X-Y-Z 1955-1961 (Box 33)
- Young, Dwight 1949-1967 (Box 33)
- Younger, Dean Edward 1965-1968 (Box 33)
- Effort to oust Dabney as Rector of Virginia Commonwealth University 1968-1971 (Box 34)
- Miscellaneous correspondence 1963-1968 (Box 34)
- Miscellaneous clippings 1953-1969 (Box 34)
- Miscellaneous clippings 1953-1969 (Box 34)
- Miscellaneous clippings ca. 1954-1968 (Box 33)